#### Curriculum Vitae

# Tahir Muhammad

Tahir.muhammad@mail.utoronto.ca Homepage.com/Tahir Linkedin.com/Tahir

#### Research Interests

My research interests are broadly focused on questions related to artificial intelligence, reinforcement learning, deep learning and statistical learning theory. I want to answer questions that enable us to understand deep learning on a new paradigm – allowing us to focus on AI alignment. In terms of application of AI, I want to focus on building tools which allows teams to build un-biased and equitable models, detect fraud entities and illicit behavior, and applications aimed at uplifting societies.

#### Education

## University of Toronto

Sep. 2015 – June 2021

Honours Bachelors of Science - Mathematical and Computational Sciences

- GPA: 3.7/4.0
- Specialization: Major in Applied Statistics and Computer Science, Minor in Economics
- Research Assistant: AI Researcher for Anti-Money Laundering, Entropy Estimation for Censored Data
- Graduate Courses: Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Advanced Statistical Learning, Multivariate Regression

# Work Experience

# Software Engineer - Big Data Platform

Feb. 2023 – Present

BlueCat Networks

- Develop scale-able data pipelines using modern tech stack to ingest 10 million rows of DNS data / day
- Optimize SQL queries to reduce report generation latency time by 27% for all company wide reports
- Replace dependency of large reports from Hadoop to Apache Iceberg, reducing AWS glue-crawlers usage by 87%, leading to a reduction of our datalake costs by 31%

# Data Scientist - Data Strategy & Engineering

Dec. 2021 – Feb. 2023

Toronto Dominion Bank

- Strategize with VPs, Business Stakeholders, and engineers to optimize different departments using data science
- Develop data visualization dashboards & automation tools, utilizing Python, Databricks, and Tableau
- Finance and Risk Data Lead, helping transfer terabytes of TD's on-perm data onto the MS Azure Cloud

# Junior Machine Learning Engineer

Sep. 2021 – Dec. 2021

Toronto Dominion Bank

- Development of NLP and Optical Character Recognition (OCR) models PvTorch & TensorFlow
- Developed data pipelines, created ML model web apps (Streamlit), and deployed to departmental platforms
- $\bullet$  Utilize advanced models such as BERT, ELMo to reach text classification accuracy of 91%

#### Innovation Data Science Intern

May 2020 – May 2021

Royal Bank of Canada

- Perform data mining, analysis, visualization, and model development to create innovative solutions for GRM
- Develop recommendation engine for data access management with a NLP chatbot for user-interaction
- Collaborate with Borealis AI team to utilize deep learning to conduct entity recognition on entire GRM datalake
- Utilize tools such as Python, PowerShell, R, Spark, Elastic Search, Hadoop & Hive, Dremio, SQL and Tableau

# Co-Founder & Software Engineer

May 2019 - Jan. 2020

Nox

- Developed a full-stack web app to allow professors to receive feedback on audience's understanding in real-time
- Utilized JavaScript, React, MongoDB, APIs and Express server to build the site with a graphical dashboard
- Scaled to 20,000 students across the 3 campuses, and verified by 5 professors at UofT

## Research & Publications

### **FruadIT** | AI Research Engineer

May 2020 – Apr. 2022

- Led a team of 4 ML engineers to investigate whether a company is requesting a fraudulent loan, to detect money laundering transactions & human trafficking entities given terabytes of transaction data
- Implement End-to-End Data Science workflow with final model reaching a false positive rate < 2%

### Monte Carlo Methods | Researcher & Engineer

Sep. 2020 - Sep. 2021

- Develop & implement algorithms for estimation of entropy and extropy for type II censored data (cancer patients)
- Co-Author and published a paper in Journal of Monte Carlo Methods and Applications

## Relevant Community Involvement

### MedicAI | Machine Learning Engineer

Oct. 2023 - Present

- Develop and deploy a deep learning model (CNNS, VGGNet, ResNets) to detect Pneumonia in images
- Leveraged TensorFlow, React, Express, MongoDB, NextJS, NodeJS and AWS Sagemaker, Lambda, & EKS

### **QuranJourney** | Full Stack Software Engineer

May 2021 – Jan. 2022

- Build, design app architecture, implement and deploy advanced features for the biggest mosque in Canada (ISNA)
- Developed sophisticated tools for analysis and studying the Quran and Hadiths, utilized by over 1000 users/month

# Glucose Vision | Consultant - ML Engineer

Sep. 2021 – Dec. 2021

- Guide development team through computer vision tasks such as object detection and image segmentation
- Eliminated team's blocker of past 4 months within 4 weeks of consultation

### RBC Technical Curriculum | President, Software Engineering Instructor

Sep. 2020 – May 2021

- Instructed multiple python boot camps to help the business teams become more technically advanced
- Founded the Enterprise Risk chapter where I organized, lead, taught and empowered others to build with code

# Teaching Experience (University of Toronto)

• CSC311: Machine Learning — Teaching Assistant (Enrollment: 36 students)	2021
• STA238: Data Analysis II — Teaching Assistant (56 students)	2021
• STA218: Statistics for Management — Head Teaching Assistant (70 students)	2021
• STA130: Introduction to Data Science — Teaching Assistant (37 students)	2020
• STA107: Probability and Reasoning—Teaching Assistant (46 students)	2020
• MAT223: Linear Algebra I — FSG Leader (12 students)	2020
• CSC108: Introduction to Programming — FSG Leader (15 students)	2020

## Certifications & Achievements

• Generative AI Course   Grade: 100%	2023
• Supervised Learning Course   Grade: 100%	2022
• Advanced Learning Algorithms Course   Grade: 100%	2022
$\bullet$ Unsupervised Learning, Recommenders, Reinforcement Learning Course   Grade: $99.18\%$	2022
• Neural Networks and Deep Learning Course   Grade: 97.3%	2021
• $4^{th}/300$ students for Big Data and AI Case Competition	2021
• Best Research Implementation Project for Nox — (Implemented in UofT CS classrooms after)	2019

### **Technical Skills**

Languages: Python, Java, C/C++, SQL (Postgres), JavaScript, Linux (bash), Spark & Scala Packages: pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, PyTorch, scikit-learn, Statsmodel, Tensorflow, MLFlow

Software: AWS (S3, Lambda, EKS), Apache Flink, Docker, Airflow, Kubernetes, Databricks & Gitlab CI/CD

Statistics & ML: Supervised & Unsupervised Learning, Time-series, Neural Networks, Bayesian Stats, A/B Testing

#### References

Prof. Luai Al Labadi UofT | Statistical Sciences luai.allabadi@utoronto.ca

Dr. Carlo Lisi TD Bank | Sr. Manager carlo.lisi@gmail.com

Roxana Zamfir RBC | Director zamfir.roxana@gmail.com